Hi again. In this video,
we're going to discuss influencing
the people around you.
I'll describe the four steps of
influencing and some common
influencing mistakes.
There are a few techniques that
project managers can use to
influence the people
they work with,
both within a team and beyond it.
But first, what do we
mean by influencing?
Influencing is the ability to
alter another person's
thinking or behaviors.
We'll discuss the concept
of influencing in
the context of our Plant Pals
project at Office Green.
Let's say that your team
would like to partner with
a well-known chocolate
manufacturer
to create a bundle deal.
With this deal, the client
could choose to add on
a high-quality chocolate bar
with each plant they purchase.
You decide to send an initial
email to a partnership
Manager at the
chocolate manufacturer
to gauge their
interest in the idea,
and ultimately influence
them to work with you.
So, how do you go about
writing that email that
effectively influences
your audience
to consider your idea?
Well, it turns out
there are four tried
and true steps of
effective influencing.
Leadership expert, Dr.
Jay A Conger identifies
the steps to
effective influencing
as: establish credibility,
frame for common ground,
provide evidence and
connect emotionally.
Let's discuss each step.
The first step to
effective influencing is
to establish credibility.
During this step,
you make the case
for why your audience
should listen to you.
According to Dr. Conger,
credibility comes
from two sources,
expertise, and relationships.
You need to demonstrate
to your audience
that you're an expert
on a given topic,
whether that's through
professional experience,
extensive research,
or something else, and
you need to demonstrate
relationship credibility by
establishing that you're honest,
trustworthy, and someone
who they want to work with.
To establish credibility,
you might kick off
your Office Green email by
greeting the recipient by name,
then writing something like,
"I'm Elita, a lead project
manager at Office Green.
Your colleague, Alex, passed
on your contact information.
Alex and I worked together
to launch new services at
Office Green before she
joined your organization."
In these opening lines,
you've established expertise,
credibility by
introducing your role
at office green and by
suddenly highlighting that you've
launched new services
in the past.
To demonstrate
relationship credibility,
you've established that
you and the recipient
have a shared contact
who has worked closely
with you in the past
and can vouch for
your trustworthiness and
emotional intelligence.
The second step is to
frame for common ground.
In this step, you'll
make the case
for how your idea can
benefit your audience.
To determine this, you'll need
a strong understanding of your
audience and their values.
In essence, what about your
idea will appeal to them,
and how will they stand to
benefit from agreeing
to your idea?
In our Office Green email,
you might establish that you've
researched their
organization extensively
and believe that this new service
might align with their
current offerings.
For example, you might
write something like this,
"We're launching a
service to provide
top clients with desk
plants and we'd like to
explore a bundle offering to pair
high-quality chocolate
with each plant order.
I've admired your organizations
push in recent years to work with
other lifestyle and
wellness brands and I
think there may be
a great opportunity
for us to collaborate."
In this portion of the email,
you've established
that you've done
your research on the
organization and that
their previous
partnerships indicate that
working together
might be a great fit.
The next step is to
provide evidence.
In this step, you'll
make your case through
hard data and persuasive
storytelling.
Numbers aren't strong
enough on their own.
They need stories
to liven them up.
In our Office Green email,
you might appeal to your
recipient with a line like,
"We recently surveyed clients to
gauge interest in this
kind of offering,
and your brand came
up again and again."
In this example, you
provided evidence
through the results of
client surveys which showed
overwhelmingly positive
brand recognition
for our shared audience.
The last step is to
connect emotionally.
In this step, you'll
demonstrate to your audience
that you're emotionally
committed to your
idea and you'll do
your best to match
their emotional state.
In our Office Green email,
you might demonstrate
an emotional connection
by tapping into
their brand ethos.
For example, you might
write something like,
"We've been following
your profile
on Instagram and love your posts
on chocolate's connection to
living a well and
balanced lifestyle.
Perhaps we can discuss combining
forces to bring this
message to an even
wider audience," and then
you end your note with
a friendly closer,
something like, "If
you're interested,
I'd love to connect
and share what
our partner program
is all about."
To recap, establishing
credibility,
framing for common ground,
providing evidence and
connecting emotionally,
are four proven, effective steps
you can apply when attempting
to influence others.
Dr. Conger also identified four
common mistakes that people make
when attempting to
influence others.
They'll often approach their
audience too aggressively,
and that tends to put
people off ideas entirely.
They might also
resist compromise,
which is crucial for any
kind of mutual agreement.
They'll focus too much on
developing their argument for
the idea and not enough time
establishing credibility,
framing for common ground,
providing evidence and connecting
emotionally, and they'll
assume that they can work out
an agreement through
just one conversation.
These mistakes can
jeopardize your attempts to
influence others and limit
your ability to
build relationships,
so be mindful of these common
mistakes when preparing
to pitch another person
on your big idea.
Great job. Now you know the
four steps of influencing,
as well as some common
mistakes that people
make when attempting
to influence others.
Coming up, you'll
learn more about
personal and organizational
sources of influencing power.
Meet you in the next video.